A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, History of the University FA226
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, History of the University
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA226
1 Cubic Feet 2 boxes and 5 volumes
2 boxes and 5 volumes.
Biographical/Historical note
The work of The Institute concentrated on basic research. The hope was that the discoveries might, in the long run, be applied to the public welfare, but the basic purpose was to provide an environment for exploratory original research by individuals under no compulsion to produce immediately useful results.
Scientific work of The Institute was first carried on through grants-in-aid made to researchers in scattered laboratories. This program decreased as the Institute's own laboratories developed. July 1, 1904 temporary quarters were rented at 127 East 50th Street, New York and work began there about Nov. 1, 1904. Those recruited for the first staff were Eugene L. Opie, Samuel J. Meltzer, Hideyo Noguchi and Joshua Edwin Sweet. Added to the staff very shortly were Phoebus Aaron Theodor Levene and John Auer. Alexis Carrel joined The Institute in 1906 and Jacques Loeb in 1910. On June 13, 1907 the Board of Directors voted to establish various classes of association with The Institute. The classes were: Member (for an indefinite period); Associate Member (for five year periods; amended in 1911 Rules to "a term of years); Associate of The Institute; Fellow of The Institute; Scholar of The Institute (which was dropped in the Rules amended 1928). The first Members of The Institute were Simon Flexner, S.J. Meltzer, E.L. Opie, and P.A.T. Levene.
In April 1906 the Central Laboratory with animal house and power house, located on York Avenue and 66th Street were ready for use. Simon Flexner, the first Director of the laboratories had been unanimously elected Director of The Institute on Oct. 25, 1902. However, not until a meeting on Jan. 17, 1920 did the Board make clear its sense that these were two offices, both held by Simon Flexner. The Office of Director of The Institute was clearly added in amended Rules Oct. 18, 1924. Simon Flexner was Director of The Institute and Director of the laboratories until his retirement in 1935. He was succeeded in both offices by Herbert S. Gasser, 1935-1953.
In 1910, at the York Avenue site a Hospital was opened so that the investigations of the Laboratories could be supplemented by the study of certain diseases as they actually occur in man. The Rules for the Scientific Directors as adopted on Jan. 21, 1911, provided that The Institute be comprised of two coordinate departments, Laboratories and Hospital. Rufus Cole was the first Director of the Department of the Hospital and continued in this post until his retirement in 1937 when he was succeeded by Thomas M. Rivers. The Hospital accepted only a limited number of patients, limited further to classes of diseases under study in the Hospital laboratories. The By-Laws of the Corporation provided that The Institute make no charge to persons treated at the Hospital for professional care rendered or for board and lodging. Classes of appointment to the Hospital were Physician, Assistant Physician, Resident Physician, Superintendent and Assistant Superintendent. In 1946 an amendment to the Rules provided that the titles be as follows: Physician-in-Chief to the Hospital; Physician to the Hospital; Assistant Physician to the Hospital; Resident Associate Physician; Senior Assistant Physician; Superintendent of the Hospital; Assistant Superintendent of the Hospital.
In 1914, at a location about three miles from Princeton, N.J. with Theobald Smith as Director, a new Department of Animal Pathology was established. In June 1915 the Rules were amended to make this coordinate with the Departments of Laboratories and Hospital. When Theobald Smith retired in 1930 Carl TenBroeck became Director of the Department which in 1931 was expanded by the appointment of Louis O. Kunkel who headed the new division of plant pathology into the Department of Animal and Plant Pathology.
The Director of each Department was appointed by the Board of Scientific Directors, and the Director of The Institute by the Corporation. In the different departments separate laboratories were organized under the guidance of a Member or Associate Member. The broad divisions of scientific fields varied from time to time in accordance with scientific developments and the interests of the Members, but always with consultation, approval and direction of the Board of Scientific Directors.
In 1953, after the retirement of Herbert S. Gasser, an extensive reorganization was undertaken. Thomas M. Rivers, who served for two years as Vice-President of the Corporation and at the same time, Director of the Laboratories, Director of the Department of the Hospital and Physician-in-Chief to the Hospital retired in 1955. The position of Director of The Institute was abolished and also the organization into departments.
On and after November 19, 1954 when the Charter of the Corporation was amended so that the Corporation became part of the University of the State of New York The Institute had the power to confer degrees. On June 27, 1958 by amendment to the Charter the corporate name was changed to The Rockefeller Institute and on May 27, 1965 the Charter of The Institute was amended in its entirety and the name changed to The Rockefeller University.
The University is organized into laboratories, each headed by one or two senior scientists rather than into categorical departments. The scientific work of the laboratories is under the direction of the President.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 400
Separated Materials
ALL VOLUMES REMOVED TO RAC LIBRARY 8/9/1988.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Operations management; Medical education; Medical sciences; Medical research; Life sciences; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Biology -- Research; Rockefeller University; Greene, Jerome D.; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller Foundation; Rockefeller, John D. (John Davison)
- Theophil Mitchell Prudden, 1901-1924
  Scope and Contents note
  Unfinished manuscript and drafts.
  History of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research in manuscript form as planned and written by T. Mitchell Prudden, member of the first Board of Scientific Directors and first chairman of the Executive Committee.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged by chapters and subjects.
  - untitled (Box 1)
    Part 1 in 15 chapters; Part 2 unfinished.
    Listing of chapter headings followed in arrangement.
    Also included is a 14 page exchange between Dr. Prudden and Dr. Peyton Rous on tumor cells in the form of questions and answers. Not dated and no information of the circumstances under which it took place.
    5 letters from E.B. Smith to Dr. Flexner and Dr. James Murphy, 1926-1934 referring to various parts of Prudden's History.
  - untitled (Box 2)
    Contains working copies, some originals, some revised copies, some handwritten notes of chapters as found in Box 1.
    Also includes a folder of reprints, clippings and notes used in writing the history.
    Also includes drafts of various reports prepared for the Scientific Directors. Early drafts of the Report with special Reference to a Permanent Endowment, including Hospital plans; plans for a farm; plans for Pension and Retiring Plans; Plans for a third section of the Institute. See Minutes of Scientific Directors, Feb. 10, 1910 for final form.
    Also includes a summary accompanying the Report of Oct. 1914 on the Establishment of New Activities for the Promotion of Public Health (handwritten notations of planned changes)
- Books and early articles
  - Flexner, Abraham. Medical education; a comparative study. New York, The Macmillan Company, 1925, 324 pp. (Volume 1)
    Scope and Contents
    The volumes reflect, in large measure, the ideas and thinking that were governing concepts in the direction of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research.
    Separated Materials
    ALL VOLUMES REMOVED TO RAC LIBRARY 8/9/1988.
  - Billroth, Theodor. The Medical sciences in the German universities; a study in the history of civilization. Trans. from the German with an introduction by William H. Welch. New York, The Macmillan Company, 1924, 292 pp. (Volume 2)
  - Turner, Thomas B. Heritage of excellence; the Johns Hopkins medical institutions, 1914-1947. Baltimore, Maryland, The Johns Hopkins University Press, 1974, 1914-1917; 648 pp. (Volume 3)
    A third volume which is primarily a history of The Johns Hopkins Medical Institution, 1914-1917 has many references to people, programs and philosophy of The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research that it serves as historical background for The Rockefeller University. This copy was presented to the University by the author and is inscribed as follows: "To The Rockefeller University / In recognition of many years of close association between the faculties of the two institutions. / Thomas B. Turner, M.D., March 1977".
  - Donald A. Dewsbury, editor. Leaders in the Study of Animal Behavior. Autobiographical Perspectives. (Lewisburg: Bucknell University Press; London and Toronto: Associated University Presses, 1985) (Volume 4)
    Includes chapters by Donald R. Griffin (5); Peter Marler (13).
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Received 12 June. 1985 (S.W. Mirsky).
  - Robert Olby. The Path to the Double Helix. (Seattle: University of Washington Press, 1974) (Volume 5)
    Received 12 June 1985 (S.W. Mirsky).
  - Articles by Burton J. Hendrick
    These are article citations are provided for reference purposes only. The individual articles are not contained in the collection.
    - "Work at The Rockefeller Institute. The transplanting of animal organs" McClure's Magazine 32: 367-383, 1909 February
    - "Conquering spinal meningitis. What The Rockefeller Institute has done for children" McClure's Magazine 32: 594-604, 1909 April
  - Articles indexed in the Reader's Guide to Periodical Literature
    - "Establishment" Popular Science. 62: 564, 1903 April 5
    - "Plans for the Institute" Independent 55: 467, 1903 February 26
    - "Dedication" Science n.s. 24: 12-3, 1906 July 6
    - "Home for medical research" H.T. Wade il. Sci. Am. 100: 21 2, 1909 January 9
    - "Sketch of development" L.E. Holt, Science n.s. 24: 1-6, 1906 July 6
    - "Temple of preventive medicine" F. Strother World's Work 13: 8324, 1906 December 6
    - "Work at the institute" B.J. Hendrick
      [See above]
    - "Work of the institute" H.T. Wade, il. Reviews of Reviews 39: 183-91, 1909 February